A Finding Aid to the A.G. (Abel George) Warshawsky papers, circa 1900-1988, in the Archives of American Art aaa.warsabel
Archives of American Art
A.G. (Abel George) Warshawsky papers
circa 1900-1988
aaa.warsabel
Archives of American Art
3.8 Linear feet
The papers of A.G. (Abel George) Warshawsky date from circa 1900 to 1988 and measure 3.8 linear feet. the papers contain biographical materials; scattered correspondence, most of which consists of letters from Warshawsky to his wife Ruth; writings, including versions of Warshawsky's autobiography; printed materials; two scrapbooks; photographs and eight photo albums; twenty-six sketchbooks; and artworks by Warshawsky and others.
Warshawsky, A. G., (Abel G.), 1883-1962
Arrangement note
The collection is arranged as 8 series.
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1923-circa 1940 (3 folders; Box 1)
Series 2: Correspondence, 1941-1964 (4 folders; Box 1)
Series 3: Writings and Notes, circa 1930-circa 1950 (0.4 linear feet; Box 1)
Series 4: Printed Material, 1920-1964 (0.2 linear feet; Box 1, 6, OV 12)
Series 5: Scrapbooks, 1913-1960 (0.3 linear feet; Box 1, 9)
Series 6: Photographs, circa 1910-1988 (1.4 linear feet; Box 1-2, 5, 7-8, OV 10)
Series 7: Sketchbooks, circa 1910-circa 1950 (1.0 linear feet; Box 2-3, 5-6)
Series 8: Artwork, circa 1900-1951 (0.5 linear feet; Box 3-5, OV 11)
Biographical/Historical note
Impressionist painter A.G. Warshawsky (1883-1962) was active in Paris and Monterey, California.
Abel George "Buck" Warshawsky was born in Sharon, Pennsylvania in 1883. He spent his childhood in Cleveland, Ohio where he studied at the Cleveland Art Institute. Warshawsky moved to New York where he studied at the Art Students League and the National Academy of Design. His brother, Alexander also became an artist.
In 1909, Abel Warshawsky left the U.S. for Paris where he remained for thirty years. There, he developed his unique style, combining Impressionism and Realism. He returned to the United States annually, mostly to sell his paintings, but remained active in the Parisian art scene until 1939. He exhibited his works in Cleveland, New York, Chicago, San Francisco, Los Angeles, and Paris.
Before the start of World War II, Warshawsky left Paris and settled in Monterey, California. Warshawsky married Ruth Tate in 1941. He died from heart failure in 1962. His works are in the permanent collections of the Akron Art institute, the Cleveland museum of Art, the Luxembourg Museum, the De Young Museum, the Petit Palais, and the Los Angeles County Museum of Art.
Conditions Governing Access note
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington D.C. Research Facility. Contact Reference Services for more information.
Separated Materials note
The Western Reserve Historical Society in Cleveland, Ohio holds the Abel G. Warshawsky Family papers.
Scope and Contents note
The papers of A.G. (Abel George) Warshawsky date from circa 1900 to 1988 and measure 3.8 linear feet. The papers contain biographical materials; scattered correspondence, most of which consists of letters from Warshawsky to his wife Ruth; writings, including versions of Warshawsky's autobiography; printed materials; two scrapbooks; photographs and eight photo albums; twenty-six sketchbooks; and artworks by Warshawsky and others.
Biographical materials consist of passports, an identification card, and a Who's Who entry. Correspondence is scattered and contains letters written by A.G. Warshawsky to his wife Ruth. There are also telegrams of congratulations for the Warshawskys' 1941 marriage and a few letters from museums and institutions regarding Warshawsky's art.
Writings and notes include three versions of Warshawsky's autobiography entitled: "My Brush with Life," "Adventures with Color and Brush," and "Warshawsky's Autobiography." The autobiography concerns his life in Paris, activities, and acquaintances as a young art student in Paris. Also found are other writings about art and a notebook.
Printed material includes exhibition catalogs, xeroxed copies of news clippings and a clippings file concerning Warshawsky's career, published material, and reproductions of works of art. Also found is a printed portfolio comprised of an introduction to Warshawsky and reproductions of his paintings.
There is one original and one xeroxed scrapbook, containing news clippings, and exhibition materials from 1913 to 1960.
Photographs includes eight photo albums and photographs of Warshawsky, of family and friends, and of works of art. The bulk of the photo albums contain photographs of works of art. Two photo albums consist of personal photos of Warshawsky and his wife Ruth in their home in California. Other photographs are of Warshawsky painting in his studio, with his art, and of his wife, family, friends, and artist models.
Twenty-six sketchbooks are primarily in pencil and are undated or unidentified. Some sketchbooks include place names such as Monterey and Carmel, California, Mexico, and Paris.
Additional artwork includes loose sketches and a print by Warshawsky. Also found are prints and drawings by others, including Goya, Edwin Kaufman, and Paul de Lassence.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The bulk of the A.G. Warshawsky papers were donated in 1996 by Froma Goldberg, Warshawsky's niece. In 1978, Ruth Warshawsky donated a typescript copy of her husband's autobiography, "My Brush with Life."
Existence and Location of Copies note
The collection was digitized in 2015 and is available via the Archives of American Art's Website.
de Lassence, Paul; Goya, Francisco, 1746-1828; Kaufman, Edwin; Warshawsky, Ruth; Art students--France--Paris; Art--Study and teaching--France--Paris; Artists' studios--Photographs; Expatriate painters--France--Paris; Impressionism (Art); Painters--California--Los Angeles; Paris (France); Photograph albums; Photographs; Scrapbooks; Sketchbooks; Sketches
- Biographical Material, 1923-circa 1940; Series 1; 3 Folders Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  Biographical materials include a membership card, three passports, and a Who's Who entry for A.G. Warshawsky.
  Existence and Location of Copies note
  This series has been scanned in its entirety.
  - Identification Card, Société de la Légion d'honneur, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Passports, 1923-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Who's Who Entry, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Correspondence, 1941-1964; Series 2; 4 Folders Box 1
  Correspondence includes letters from A.G. Warshawsky to his wife, Ruth, telegrams, and scattered letters from museums and institutions concerning his art.
  - Abel Warshawsky to Ruth Tate Warshawsky, 1941-1950 (Box 1, Folder 4-5)
  - Telegrams, 1941 June (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Museums and Institutions to Abel and Ruth Warshawsky, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Writings and Notes, circa 1930-circa 1950; Series 3; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Writings by A.G. Warshawsky include versions of his autobiography entitled: "My Brush with Life," "Adventures with Color and Brush," and a later typescript entitled "Warshawsky's Autobiography." Also found are other writings on art and a notebook.
  Warshawsky's autobiography records his life in Paris, activities, and acquaintances as a young art student in Paris. He recalls meeting Winslow Homer, (Gustave) Dounies Courtois, Modigliani, Paul Signac and Auguste Renoir. Mentioned are Jack Casey, Arthur Burdett Frost, Jr., Samuel Halpert, Ben Kafka, David Karfunkle, Leon Kroll, Louis Loeb, Henry Mathes, Ivan Olinsky, Alfred Rigny, Hugo Robus, Daniel Gale Turnbull, Alexander Warshawsky (his brother), Wythe Williams, and William Zorach.
  - "The Barnums of Art," by A.G. Warshawsky, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - [After Ethel's Funeral], by A.G. Warshawsky, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - "My Brush with Life," by A.G. Warshawsky, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 10-14)
  - "Adventures with Color and Brush," by A.G. Warshawsky, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 15-16)
  - [Craftsmanship], by A.G. Warshawsky, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Warshawsky's Autobiography," by A.G. Warshawsky, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Notebook, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Printed Material, 1920-1964; Series 4; 0.2 Linear feet Box 1, 6, OV 12
  Printed materials include exhibition catalogs, clippings and xeroxed copies of clippings relating to Warshawsky's career, an issue of Art and Archaeology, and reproductions of works of art. Also found is film publicity materials for The Story Behind the Film, Creation of a Portrait featuring Warshawsky. There is a portfolio publication on Warshawsky that includes reproductions of his work of art.
  - Exhibition Catalog, 1958-1962 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Clippings (xerox), circa 1930-1964 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Art and Archaeology, Vol IX, No. 6, 1920 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Film Publicity Material, The Story Behind the Film, Creation of a Portrait, circa 1950 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Reproductions of Works of Art, circa 1930 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Clippings File, 1949 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Portfolio, 1927 (Box OV 12, Folder 1)
- Scrapbooks, 1913-1960; Series 5; 0.3 Linear feet Box 1, 9
  There are two scrapbooks, one a photocopy, containing printed materials.
  - Scrapbook 1 (xerox), 1913-1960 (Box 1, Folder 26-27)
  - Scrapbook 2, circa 1910-circa 1930 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Photographs, circa 1910-1988; Series 6; 1.4 Linear feet Box 1-2, 5, 7-8, OV 10
  Eight photo albums house photos of A.G. and Ruth Warshawsky, of family and friends, and of works of art. The majority of the photo albums consist of photos of portraits and other works of art by Warshawsky. There are two photo albums with personal photographs of Warshawsky, Ruth, their home and studio in Monterey, California. Photos of Warshawsky include snapshots and portraits, some of which depict the artist painting in his studio or with his art. Other photos of Warshawsky are with his wife, family, and friends. Also found are photographs of models, probably used as inspiration for Warshawsky's art and of works of art in situ.
  - Photo Album 1, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 28)
    Monterey, California. Includes Portraits, Warshawsky painting in studio, homes, and landscapes. Likely taken by Max Reichmann.
  - Photo Album 2, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 29)
    Includes photos of portraits by Warshawsky. Album was dismantled and pages with identification were photocopied.
  - Photo Album 3, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 30)
    Includes photographs of portraits by Warshawsky.
  - Photo Album 4, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 31-32)
  - Photo Album 5, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 33-34)
    Includes personal and studio photos. Also found are clippings.
  - Photo Album 6, 1901-circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 35)
    Oversized material housed in Box 7. Contains photos of works of art, portraits,and sketches.
  - Photo Album 7, circa 1940 (Box 1, Folder 36)
    Oversized material housed in Box 8. Includes photos of works of art and an exhibition catalog.
  - Photo Album 8, circa 1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F1. Includes photos of works of art.
  - A.G. Warshawsky, 1952-1957 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F7 and OV 10.
  - A.G. and Ruth Warshawsky, circa 1956 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Ruth Warshawsky, circa 1950-1956 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Ruth Warshawsky with Art, circa 1960 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Warshawsky with Family and Friends, circa 1950-1958 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Family, circa 1910-circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 6-7)
  - Filming a Movie, circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    Includes A.G. and Ruth Warshawsky, Joseph P. Davies, and J.R. Kray
  - Models, circa 1920-circa 1940 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Works of Art, In Situ, circa 1930 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Works of Art, circa 1940-1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F9 and OV 10.
  - Negatives, Slides, and Transparencies, circa 1950-circa 1970 (Box 2, Folder 12-13)
  - Oversized Photo Album 8, Scanned with Box 1, F37, circa 1960 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Oversized Photo of A.G. Warshawsky, Scanned with Box 2, F1, 1952-1957 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Oversized Photos of Works of Art, Scanned with Box 2, F11, circa 1940-1988 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Oversized Photo Album 6, Scanned with Box 1, F35, circa 1940 (Box 7)
  - Oversized Photo Album 7, Scanned with Box 1, F36, 1901-circa 1940 (Box 8)
  - Oversized Photos of Warshawsky and Works of Art, Scanned with Box 2, F1, 11, circa 1940-1988 (Box OV 10)
- Sketchbooks, circa 1910-circa 1950; Series 7; 1 Linear feet Box 2-3, 5-6
  There are twenty-six sketchbooks by A.G. Warshawsky, likely dating from circa 1910 to circa 1950. Most are unlabeled, however a few places are referenced, including Monterey and Carmel, California, Paris, France, and Mexico.
  - Sketchbook 1, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    Monterey and Carmel
  - Sketchbook 2, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    Mexico
  - Sketchbook 3, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Taxco, Mexico
  - Sketchbook 4, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    Paris
  - Sketchbook 5, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Sketchbook 6, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbook 7, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook 8, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook 9, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook 10, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook 11, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Sketchbook 12, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    Fragment
  - Sketchbook 13, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Sketchbook 14, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Sketchbook 15, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Sketchbook 16, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Sketchbook 17, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Sketchbook 18, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Sketchbook 19, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook 20, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook 21, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook 22, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Sketchbook 23, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Sketchbook 24, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Sketchbook 25, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Sketchbook 26, circa 1910-circa 1950 (Box 6, Folder 6)
- Artwork, circa 1900-1951; Series 8; 0.5 Linear feet Box 3-5, OV 11
  Additional artwork consists of pencil and pen and ink sketches and a print by A.G. Warshawsky. Also found are prints and drawings by others, with some signatures illegible. Some artworks by others are inscribed to Warshawsky as "Buck" and dated. Other artists include Goya, Edwin Kaufman, and Paul de Lassence.
  - Loose Sketches, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F8. Intended to be framed.
  - Loose Sketches, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Intended to be framed
  - Loose Sketches, circa 1900-circa 1940 (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Print, Likely by Warshawsky, circa 1920 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F5.
  - Artwork by Others, circa 1920s-1951 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    Oversized material housed in Box 5, F6 and OV11.
  - Oversized Print by Warshawsky, Scanned with Box 4, F4, circa 1920 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Oversized Loose Sketches, Scanned with Box 4, F2-3, circa 1900-circa 1940 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others, Scanned with Box 4, F5, circa 1920s (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Oversized Sketches Intended to be Framed, Scanned with Box 3, F1, circa 1900-circa 1950 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Oversized Artwork by Others, Scanned with Box 4, F5, circa 1920s-1951 (Box OV 11)